Finding Aid for University College (University of Michigan) Records 1922-1930
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University College (University of Michigan) records 1922-1930
University of Michigan. University College.
1.5 linear foot
Correspondence, reports, and minutes detailing effort to establish a University College at the University of Michigan.
87337 Bimu B316 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the College of Engineering (Donor no. 1884 ) in 1954.
The records are open for research.
The 1920s at the University of Michigan saw a growing interest of the faculties in progressive educational programs and reorganization within the university structure. In his first presidential report, Clarence C. Little raised the question of establishing junior and senior colleges, and in late 1926 and 1927 a University Senate Committee on Undergraduate Studies met to survey the present system and offer suggestions for improvement.
The Committee proposed that a University College be organized, with its own dean and faculty composed of members of the other university schools and departments. They further recommended that the college determine its own requirements for admission, and have jurisdiction over all students during their first two undergraduate years.
Because there was little unanimity of opinion among faculty as to the feasibility or even the value of the University College project, the year 1927-28 was devoted to further study. During this time, various committees were appointed to outline possible curriculum programs and deal with issues such as faculty, teaching methods, and the selection, placement and guidance of students.
Discussed by the separate faculties, committee findings were unfavorably received by both the Engineering College and the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, the two largest units directly concerned. Their objections were based on cost, the problems of reorganization, the possible jeopardization of student interests, and the emerging sense of greater distinctions among the various disciplines. Despite these complaints, the Regents remained enthusiastic and authorized an executive committee with the intention of implementing the plan as early as September 1929.
On January 21, 1929, President Little handed the Regents his resignation, recommending that the University College be abandoned unless his successor should decide to personally sponsor it. Although the Regents instructed the executive committee to continue its consideration of the plans, they decided to defer action until determining the views of incoming President Alexander Ruthven.
In February 1930, Dr. Ruthven declared that he "favored the improvement of educational facilities and methods without the fundamental reorganization and the expense which would be involved in the University College." Although the project never came to fruition, many of the same ends were achieved during Dr. Ruthven's administration in an atmosphere of educational and administrative progress.
The University College record group is comprised of materials documenting the project at its peak from 1926 to 1930, with some relevant printed matter dating back to 1922. The records offer a fairly complete administrative history of the University College development, with a minor emphasis on criticism and feedback. Materials are divided into two series: Committee Files and Correspondence, Statements and Miscellaneous Files. Of the two, the Committee Files is more valuable in providing a comprehensive view of the University College project.
Subjects:
Universities and colleges.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan. University College.
- Committee Files
  The Committee Files series (1.0 linear foot) chronicles the activity of the various committees appointed to determine the value of a University College organization. In addition to the Senate Committee, Regents Committee, Executive and General Committees, several sub- and special committees are represented, illustrating the effort which was made to target and study various issues concerning the undergraduate population. Specifically, these issues were admissions, curriculum, faculty and teaching methods, organization, and the selection, placement, and guidance of students.
  Materials present in the Committee File include meeting minutes and reports, correspondence, memoranda, general information, and printed matter used for reference. The amount of information varies greatly from folder to folder depending upon the size and activities of the committee.
  - Senate Committee
    - General, 1926-28 (Box 1)
    - Minutes January 18, 1927-January 26, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Remarks on University College (Box 1)
    - Survey on Higher Education 1922-1924 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Undergraduate Studies
      - General 1927 (Box 1)
      - Reports August 1927-May 1928 (Box 1)
    - Curriculum Committee
      - General 1927 (Box 1)
      - Minutes February 9, 1927-February 19, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Regents Committee
    - Correspondence, October 4, 1928-March 19 1929 (Box 1)
    - Financial Records March 1929 (Box 1)
    - Formation 1928 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, April 24, 1928-November 23 1928 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee
    - Ballot (Box 1)
    - Correspondence June 1927-May 1929 (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - Minutes October 2-November 28, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Minutes December 5, 1928-January 23, 1929 (Box 1)
    - Memoranda on University College September 17, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Memorandum Concerning the work of the Sub-committee on Curriculum April 8, 1929 (Box 1)
  - General Committee
    - Clippings October 28, 1927-February 17, 1928 (Box 1)
    - General 1927 (Box 1)
    - List of References on Higher Education September 1927 (Box 1)
    - Minutes
      - November 11-30, 1927 (Box 1)
      - December 14, 1927-January 23, 1928 (Box 1)
    - February 1-14, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Personnel Methods, July 1928 (Box 1)
    - Reports (Box 1)
  - Sub-Committees
    - Curriculum, Sub-Committee on
      - Correspondence November 1927-January 1929 (Box 1)
      - General (Box 1)
      - Group Programs November 1927-January 1929 (Box 1)
      - Group Programs-Suggestions by Departments January 1928 (Box 1)
      - Minutes December 13, 1927 (Box 1)
      - Reports January 1928-January 1929 (Box 1)
    - Entrance Requirements, Sub-Committee on
      - Minutes, 10/15/28- November 11, 1928 (Box 1)
      - Report on College Entrance Conference April 1929 (Box 1)
    - Faculty, Sub-Committee on
      - General (Box 1)
      - Minutes, November 22 1927 (Box 1)
      - Reports December 1926-February 1928 (Box 1)
    - Organization of University College, Sub-Committee on-Report August 27, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Selection, Placement and Guidance of Students, Sub-Committee on
      - General November 1927 (Box 1)
      - Reports December 1927-January 1928 (Box 1)
      - Report, "Benefits Derived from the Segregation of Students in Technical Subjects on the Basis of Ability" (Box 1)
      - Report on Methods of Increasing the Intellectual Interest of Students at the University of Michigan October 1924 (Box 1)
    - Weekly Program, Sub-Committee on-Report November 21, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Joint Report of Sub-Committees, and Responses January 1928 (Box 1)
  - Special Committees
    - Admissions, University Committee on
      - Admissions Information September 1925-November 1928 (Box 1)
      - Minutes January 30, 1926-February 13, 1926 (Box 1)
    - Central Office of Admissions, Special Committee on-Report February 1, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Course for Orientation, Committee on-Minutes February 9-19, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Education and Methods of Teaching, Committee on-General April 30, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Program of Work, Special Committee for Committee on Organization-Report September 19, 1927 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Statements, and Miscellaneous Files
  - Gram, Lewis
    The Correspondence, Statements and Miscellaneous Files series (0.5 linear feet) contains personal correspondence of University President Clarence C. Little, under whose administration the University College proposal was explored, and professor Lewis M. Gram, who served as chairman of the executive committee.
    Of particular interest within this file are reports from other colleges and universities, as well as statements from University of Michigan schools and departments. Included here are the unfavorable views of the Engineering College and the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, which contributed to the ultimate abandonment of the project.
    News clippings and a magazine article from the Michigan Alumnus constitute the only published material directly concerning the University College plans which can be found in the collection. For information on University College history and related materials, researchers are advised to consult the card catalog at the Bentley Historical Library.
    - Correspondence
      - August-December 1928 (Box 2)
      - January-September 1929 (Box 2)
  - Little, Clarence C
    - Correspondence
      - April-November 1927 (Box 2)
      - January-March 1928 (Box 2)
      - March 1928-January 1929 (Box 2)
    - Report on University College April 24, 1928 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Alumnus-Edition on University College, March 10, 1928 (Box 2)
  - Reports and Memoranda on University College Development February-December, 1928 (Box 2)
  - Reports from Other Colleges February-October, 1928 (Box 2)
  - Statements from Schools of Business, Education and Forestry February-April, 1928 (Box 2)
  - Statements from Schools of Dentistry, Law, Medicine, and Pharmacy March-April, 1928 (Box 2)
  - Statements from School of Engineering September 1927-February 1928 (Box 2)
  - Statements from School of Literature, Science and the Arts, November 1927-February 1928 (Box 2)
  - University College-News Clippings October 8, 1928-February 3, 1929 (Box 2)